<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<page>
<page-title> Git for the OpenMath Website </page-title>

<p>The OpenMath website, including its CDs, is built from files in a
<link uri="https://github.com/">GitHub</link> git repository. The repository is publicly readable but needs
credentials to push.</p>

<p align="center"><link uri="https://github.com/OpenMath/OMSVN">https://github.com/OpenMath/OMSVN</link></p>

<p>... is the URL of that repository. This URL can be used by normal web-browsers to see the current state of repository. <link uri="https://git-scm.com/">Git</link> is a modern distributed version control system, this means that everyone has a complete version of the repository locally that needs to be synchronised with the central one. It has multiple implementations that are desktop integrated (<link uri="https://tortoisegit.org/">TortoiseGit</link>, <link uri="https://desktop.github.com/">Github Desktop</link>). Users can clone (later pull) the repository, make local changes, commit them to the local repository and push them to the central repository at GitHub. 
</p>

<p>For people more familiar with Subversion, GitHub also provides a Subversion interface at</p>

<p align="center"><link uri="https://github.com/OpenMath/OMSVN/trunk">https://github.com/OpenMath/OMSVN/trunk</link></p>

<p>
  If you find a mistake or problem with the website, please make an issue on the <link uri="https://github.com/OpenMath/OMSVN/issues">Issue tracker</link>. If you know how to, you are also welcome to use the standard GitHub workflow of <link uri="https://help.github.com/articles/using-pull-requests/">making pull requests</link>. 
</p>
<p>
  If you are interested to work on the website infrastructure, please write a mail to the infrastructure mailing list <link uri="http://openmath.org/mailman/listinfo/infrastructure">infrastructure@openmath.org</link>. 
</p>

<p>
  The website is built by an ant file, explained in the <link uri="website-build.html">website-build</link> triggered latest five minutes after a commit. This build is run with a "normal ant" with the addition of the saxon jar so that XSLT 2 and/or Saxon extensions can run. </p>
</page>
