<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<!-- $Id$  -->

<chapter id="cha_his" revisionflag="deleted">
<title>&OM; Movement</title>

<para>This chapter is a historical account of &OM; and should be regarded
as non-normative.</para>

<para>&OM; is a standard for representing mathematical objects,
allowing them to be exchanged between computer programs, stored in
databases, or published on the worldwide web.  While the original
designers were mainly developers of computer algebra systems, it
<phrase revisionflag="deleted">is now attracting</phrase> <phrase
revisionflag="added">has since attracted</phrase> interest from other
areas of scientific computation and from many publishers of electronic
documents with a significant mathematical content.  There is a strong
relationship to the MathML recommendation
<citation>MathML_2003</citation> from the Worldwide Web Consortium,
and a large overlap between the two developer communities.  MathML
deals principally with the <emphasis>presentation</emphasis> of
mathematical objects, while &OM; is solely concerned with their
semantic meaning or <emphasis>content</emphasis>.  While MathML does
have some limited facilities for dealing with content, it also allows
semantic information encoded in &OM; to be embedded inside a MathML
structure.  Thus the two technologies may be seen as highly
complementary.</para>

<section id="sec_hist">
<title>History</title>

<para>&OM; was originally developed through a series of workshops held
in Zurich (1993 and 1996), Oxford (1994), Amsterdam (1995), Copenhagen
(1995), Bath (1996), Dublin (1996), Nice (1997), Yorktown Heights
(1997), Berlin (1998), and Tallahassee (1998).  The participants in
these workshops formed a global &OM; community which was coordinated
by a Steering Committee and operated through electronic mailing groups
and ad-hoc working parties.  This loose arrangement has been
formalised through the establishment of an &OM; Society.  Up until the
end of 1996 much of the work of the community was funded through a
grant from the Human Capital and Mobility program of the European
Union, <phrase revisionflag="added"> and by</phrase> the contributions
of several institutions and individuals.  A document outlining the
objectives and basic design of &OM; was produced (later published as
<citation>Abbott_Leeuwen_Strotmann_98</citation>).  By the end of 1996
a simplified specification had been agreed upon and some prototype
implementations had come about
<citation>Dalmas_Gaetano_Watt_97</citation>.</para>

<para>In 1996 a group of European participants in &OM; decided to bid
for funding under the European Union's Fourth Framework Programme for
strategic research in information technology.  This bid was successful
and the project started in late 1997.  The principal aims of the
project were to formalise &OM; as a standard and to develop it further
through industrial applications; this process led to the OpenMath 1.0
and 1.1 standards which were endorsed at workshops in Tallahassee
(November 1998) and Eindhoven (June 1999).</para>

<para revisionflag="added">In November 1998 the &OM; Society was established to coordinate
all &OM; activities. The society is based in Helsinki, Finland and is
coordinated by the executive committee whose members are elected by the
society. The official web page of the society is
<ulink url="http://www.openmath.org">http://www.openmath.org</ulink>.</para>

<para revisionflag="added">In 2001 the European Union agreed to fund a Thematic Network
under its Fifth Framework programme to coordinate further work on
&OM; and MathML, and in particular to support a further series of workshops.  
This document is one outcome of that project, and seeks to update &OM;
in the light of recent developments in XML and of the &OM; community's
collective experience working with the old standard.</para>
</section>

<section id="sec_omsoc">
<title>&OM; Society</title>

<para revisionflag="added">In November 1998 the &OM; Society has been
established to coordinate all &OM; activities. The society is based in
Helsinki, Finland and is steered by the executive committee whose
members are elected by the society. The official web page of the
society is <ulink
url="http://www.openmath.org">http://www.openmath.org</ulink>.</para>

<para revisionflag="added">The &OM; Society continues to provide
long-term coordination of &OM; activities.  Membership is open to
anybody who is active in &OM;; for further details see the web-site
at 
<ulink url="http://www.openmath.org/society/index.html">
http://www.openmath.org/society/index.html</ulink>.</para>

</section>

</chapter>
