<page>

<page-title> The OpenMath Society </page-title>

OpenMath is an emerging
<link uri="../standard/index.html">standard</link> for
representing mathematical objects with their semantics, allowing
them to be exchanged between computer programs, stored in databases,
or published on the worldwide web.  While the original designers were
mainly developers of computer algebra systems, it is now attracting
interest from other areas of scientific computation and from many
publishers of electronic documents with a significant mathematical
content.  There is a strong relationship to the
<a href="http://www.w3.org/Math">MathML</a> recommendation
from the
<a href="http://www.w3.org">Worldwide Web Consortium</a>, 
and a large overlap between the two developer communities.  MathML deals
principally with the <I>presentation</I> of mathematical objects, while
OpenMath is solely concerned with their semantic meaning or 
<I>content</I>.  While MathML does have some limited facilities for
dealing with content, it also allows semantic information encoded in
OpenMath to be embedded inside a MathML structure.  Thus the two
technologies may be seen as highly complementary.
<p/>
Mathematical objects encoded in OpenMath can be
<ul>
<li>displayed in a browser</li>
<li>exchanged between software systems</li>
<li>cut and pasted for use in different contexts</li>
<li>verified as being mathematically sound (or not!)</li>
<li>used to make interactive documents really interactive.</li>
</ul> 
OpenMath is highly relevant for persons working with mathematics on
computers, for those working with large documents (e.g. databases,
manuals) containing mathematical expressions, and for technical and
mathematical publishing.
<p/>
The worldwide OpenMath activities are coordinated within the OpenMath Society,
based in Helsinki, Finland. It is coordinated by an <link uri="board.html" >executive committee</link>, elected by its 
<link uri="memberslist.html">members</link>, and governed by its 
<link uri="statutes.html">statutes</link>.
It organizes <link uri="../meetings/index.html">workshops</link> and hosts a 
number of <link uri="../lists/index.html">discussion lists</link>
The Society brings together tool builders,
software suppliers, publishers and authors.

</page>
