<page>
<page-title>OPENMATH SOCIETY STATUTES</page-title>
<P ALIGN="CENTER"></P>
<P ALIGN="LEFT"></P>

<H1><A NAME="SECTION00010000000000000000">
Name and location</A>
</H1>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00011000000000000000">
ARTICLE 1</A>
</H2>
The OpenMath Society, informally OMS, is an association
established in accordance with the laws of Finland.

<p/>
The Society is based in Helsinki, Finland.

<p/>

<H1><A NAME="SECTION00020000000000000000">
Purpose and nature of activities</A>
</H1>

<p/>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00021000000000000000">
ARTICLE 2</A>
</H2>
The purpose of the Society is to promote the development of all
aspects of the use of information technology in  mathematics, with
particular emphasis on the presentation and application of mathematics in
computer networks.

<p/>
In particular, the Society will, at an international level, aim to
promote the technology required for mathematical research (pure and
applied), teaching, and the use of mathematics in general.

<p/>
To achieve its aims the Society may prepare proposals and
motions, make statements, organise courses and seminars, arrange
negotiations and meetings, operate as a publisher, award grants
and represent its membership.

<p/>
To support its activities the Society may collect membership fees
from its members and may receive donations and legacies as well as
grants from both public and private sources.  The Society may own
real estate and movable property.

<p/>

<H1><A NAME="SECTION00030000000000000000">
Membership</A>
</H1>

<p/>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00031000000000000000">
ARTICLE 3</A>
</H2>
The Society may accept, as an ordinary member, any person who
supports the Society's purpose, as described in Article&#160;2 above.

<p/>
The Society may accept, as a supporting member, any person or
legal entity that wishes to support the Society's aims or
activities.

<p/>
Applications to become ordinary members and supporting members will be
considered by the Executive Committee of the Society.

<p/>
A person who has promoted the Society's activities in a
remarkable way may be invited to become the Honorary President or
an Honorary Member.  The Society's Executive Committee will propose
such invitations to a Meeting of the Society, and a General
Meeting of the Society has to agree to such an invitation.

<p/>
The number of non-Finnish members may exceed one third of the
total.

<p/>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00032000000000000000">
ARTICLE 4</A>
</H2>

<p/>
Members may terminate their membership by giving
notice in writing to the Executive Committee or to the President,
or by notifying the Society at its meeting, such notice to be recorded in the
minutes.

<p/>
The Executive Committee may decide to expel a member 
if the member has not paid the membership fees or
has otherwise neglected the duties of a member of the Society or
has damaged the reputation of the Society in some way.

<p/>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00033000000000000000">
ARTICLE 5</A>
</H2>

<p/>
Members and supporting members pay registration and membership
dues as determined by the General meeting.  The Honorary President and
Honorary Members do not pay membership fees.

<p/>

<H1><A NAME="SECTION00040000000000000000">
Organs of the Society</A>
</H1>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00041000000000000000">
ARTICLE 6</A>
</H2>
The body of the Society with decision-making powers is the
General Meeting of the Society. The executive body is the
Executive Committee of the Society.  The Executive Committee will
consist of the President and of five to seven (5-7) ordinary
members of the Society as elected by a General Meeting of the
Society.

<p/>
The period of office is the time between consecutive Annual
General Meetings.

<p/>
The Executive Committee will elect one of its members to the
position of Vice-President of the Society, and will appoint
a Secretary, Treasurer, and other necessary officers who need not
be members of the Executive Committee.

<p/>
Meetings of the Executive Committee will be convened, whenever
necessary, by the President, or in his absence by the Vice-President.
The Executive Committee will also meet whenever
at least half of its members request that it do so.

<p/>
The quorum of the Executive Committee shall be at least
half of its members plus either the President or the Vice-President.
Decisions will be determined by a simple majority of votes
cast, with the President having a casting vote in the event of a tie
except in the case of an election, which will be decided by lot.

<p/>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00042000000000000000">
ARTICLE 7</A>
</H2>
Two of the following officers together may sign on behalf of the
Society: President, Vice-President, Secretary and Treasurer.

<p/>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00043000000000000000">
ARTICLE 8</A>
</H2>

<p/>
The fiscal year shall be the calendar year. The accounts together
with the necessary accompanying documents including the Executive
Committee's report on its activities shall be submitted to the
auditors at least three weeks before the Annual General Meeting.
The auditors' report shall be submitted to the Executive
Committee at least two weeks before the Annual General Meeting.

<p/>

<H1><A NAME="SECTION00050000000000000000">
The General Meeting</A>
</H1>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00051000000000000000">
ARTICLE 9</A>
</H2>
The Annual General meetings of the Society will be convened by
the Executive Committee and the meetings take place
every  year during the period January&#160;1 - May&#160;31.

<p/>
Extraordinary General Meeting of the Society will take place
whenever a General Meeting of the Society so decides, or whenever
the Executive Committee convenes such a meeting, or whenever at
least one tenth (1/10) of the Society members request, in
writing to the Executive Committee, such a meeting.  Such a meeting
has to take place within 30 days of the request.

<p/>
In a General Meeting every member, Honorary President and
Honorary Member will have one vote.  Supporting members may be
present at meetings and participate in the discussions.

<p/>
A Decision of the Meeting will be, unless the bylaws require otherwise,
the opinion that has been supported by more than half of the
votes cast.  In the case of equal votes the President of the Meeting
will have the casting vote, except in elections which will be
decided by lot.

<p/>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00052000000000000000">
ARTICLE 10</A>
</H2>

<p/>
To convene the Society's General Meeting, the Executive Committee must give
all members at least seven days notice either by writing to them
individually or by placing an announcement in a newspaper appearing in 
the town where the Society is based.

<p/>

<H1><A NAME="SECTION00060000000000000000">
Duties of the Annual General meeting</A>
</H1>

<p/>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00061000000000000000">
ARTICLE 11</A>
</H2>

<p/>
The agenda of an Annual General Meeting will include the following items.
<ol>
<li>The opening of the meeting.</li>
<li>The election of the President of the Meeting,
a Secretary, two persons to check the minutes, and two persons to
count the votes if necessary.
</li>
<li>A motion that the Meeting has been properly convened and has the 
authority to make decisions.
</li>
<li>A motion to accept the Agenda of the Meeting.
</li>
<li>The presentation of the accounts and of the auditors reports.
</li>
<li>A motion to Confirm the financial statements and discharge those
concerned from liability.
</li>
<li>Motions to confirm the Society's plan for actions in the coming year,
confirm the budget and determine the registration and membership
dues.
</li>
<li>The election of the President and the other members
of the Executive Committee.
</li>
<li>The election of one or two auditors and their deputies.
</li>
<li>Any other matters proposed by the Executive Committee.
</li>
</ol>
<p/>
In the case that a member of the Society wishes to add an item to
the agenda of a General Meeting, they must inform the
Executive Committee in good time prior to the meeting.

<p/>

<H1><A NAME="SECTION00070000000000000000">
Amendments</A>
</H1>

<H2><A NAME="SECTION00071000000000000000">
ARTICLE 12</A>
</H2>
Any proposal to amend the statutes or to dissolve or merge the
Society must be passed by three-quarters (3/4) of the votes cast in
a General meeting.  Such a matter can be decided only if it has
been included in the Agenda of the Meeting which was sent to the
members when the meeting was convened.

<p/>
In the event of the Society being dissolved or abolished, any
assets remaining after discharge of all debts shall be
transferred to a legal body having aims similar to those of the
Society.

</page>
